<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>João Sargento-Freitas | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/authors/joao-sargento-freitas/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/authors/joao-sargento-freitas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>João Sargento-Freitas</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>João Sargento-Freitas</title>
      <link>/website/authors/joao-sargento-freitas/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intracranial Internal Carotid Artery Wall Calcification in Ischemic Strokes Treated With Thrombolysis</title>
      <link>/website/publication/intracranial-internal-carotid-artery-wall-calcification-in-ischemic-strokes-treated-with-thrombolysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/intracranial-internal-carotid-artery-wall-calcification-in-ischemic-strokes-treated-with-thrombolysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Calcifications are an important element of atherosclerotic plaques and have been used as a marker of atherosclerosis and clinical outcome predictor in different vascular territories. CT-scan, performed in the acute ischemic stroke setting, can reliably detect intracranial arterial calcifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: To investigate the association between intracranial internal carotid artery calcification and functional outcome, symptomatic intracerebral hemorrhage (sICH), recanalization, and death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We included 396 consecutive ischemic stroke patients submitted to recombinant tissue plasminogen activator treatment between January 2011 and September 2014. Admission CT-scans were reviewed to calculate the Total Carotid Syphon Calcification score. Patients were followed for up to at least 6 months post-stroke or until death. Outcome measures included evaluation of recanalization on the first 24 h (transcranial color coded Doppler or angio-CT), sICH, and assessment of functional outcome at 3 months after stroke (using modified Rankin scale).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Carotid artery wall calcification did not predict sICH, recanalization or any good outcome. However, it was a statistically significant predictor of death (OR 1.102, 95% CI [1.004-1.211], p = 0.042).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Intracranial carotid artery calcification does not increase the risk of thrombolysis-induced sICH. Patients with higher grade of carotid artery wall calcification may have a higher mortality rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Calcification; Carotid; Hemorrhage; Outcome; Stroke; Thrombolysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neurosonology Accuracy for Isolated Acute Vestibular Syndromes</title>
      <link>/website/publication/neurosonology-accuracy-for-isolated-acute-vestibular-syndromes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/neurosonology-accuracy-for-isolated-acute-vestibular-syndromes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: The clinical approach to acute vestibular syndromes is often complex for the physician. Neurosonology offers a noninvasive method to study the cervicocephalic circulation when a vascular etiology is suspected. We aim to evaluate the diagnostic accuracy of a vascular neurosonological exam in isolated acute vestibular syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: All patients submitted to cerebrovascular ultrasound and magnetic resonance imaging during the period between 2011 and 2015 with acute isolated vestibular syndrome. Those with any clinical sign of brainstem lesion on presentation were excluded. All patients performed the neuroimaging study (brain computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging) and neurologic surveillance. Neurosonological exam included all intra- and extracranial segments of the vertebrobasilar circulation. Positive ultrasound exam was defined as the presence of stenotic or occlusive disease in any of these segments related to the infarcted area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: A total of 108 patients were included: 60 (53.6%) were males (mean age: 60.75 years (standard deviation, 14.17)). In 27 patients (25.0%) a cerebral ischemic lesion was found to be the cause of the vertigo. Neurosonological assessment showed a sensitivity of 40.7% (95% confidence interval (CI): 22.4; 61.2), specificity of 100% (95% CI: 95.5; 100.0), positive predictive value (PPV) of 100% (95% CI: 71.5; 100.0), and negative predictive value (NPV) of 83.5% (95% CI: 74.6; 90.3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Our study suggests that cerebrovascular ultrasound is a highly specific method for the diagnosis of cerebrovascular vertigo. However, its low sensitivity makes it a poor candidate for screening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: neurosonology; stroke; ultrasound; vertigo; vestibular.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
