<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Isabel Santana | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/authors/isabel-santana/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/authors/isabel-santana/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Isabel Santana</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Isabel Santana</title>
      <link>/website/authors/isabel-santana/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addition of the Aβ42/40 Ratio to the Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarker Profile Increases the Predictive Value for Underlying Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Dementia in Mild Cognitive Impairment</title>
      <link>/website/publication/addition-of-the-a%CE%B24240-ratio-to-the-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarker-profile-increases-the-predictive-value-for-underlying-alzheimers-disease-dementia-in-mild-cognitive-impairment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/addition-of-the-a%CE%B24240-ratio-to-the-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarker-profile-increases-the-predictive-value-for-underlying-alzheimers-disease-dementia-in-mild-cognitive-impairment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers have been used to increase the evidence of underlying Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) pathology in mild cognitive impairment (MCI). However, CSF biomarker-based classification often results in conflicting profiles with controversial prognostic value. Normalization of the CSF Aβ42 concentration to the level of total amyloid beta (Aβ), using the Aβ42/40 ratio, has been shown to improve the distinction between AD and non-AD dementia. Therefore, we evaluated whether the Aβ42/40 ratio would improve MCI categorization and more accurately predict progression to AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Our baseline population consisted of 197 MCI patients, of which 144 had a follow-up ≥ 2 years, and comprised the longitudinal study group. To establish our own CSF Aβ42/40 ratio reference value, a group of 168 AD-dementia patients and 66 neurological controls was also included. CSF biomarker-based classification was operationalized according to the framework of the National Institute of Aging-Alzheimer Association criteria for MCI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: When using the core CSF biomarkers (Aβ42, total Tau and phosphorylated Tau), 30% of the patients fell into the high-AD-likelihood (HL) group (both amyloid and neurodegeneration markers positive), 30% into the low-AD-likelihood group (all biomarkers negative), 28% into the suspected non-Alzheimer pathophysiology (SNAP) group (only neurodegeneration markers positive) and 12% into the isolated amyloid pathology group (only amyloid-positive). Replacing Aβ42 by the Aβ42/40 ratio resulted in a significant increase in the percentage of patients with amyloidosis (42-59%) and in the proportion of interpretable biological profiles (61-75%), due to a reduction by half in the number of SNAP cases and an increase in the proportion of the HL subgroup. Survival analysis showed that risk of progression to AD was highest in the HL group, and increased when the Aβ42/40 ratio, instead of Aβ42, combined with total Tau and phosphorylated Tau was used for biomarker-based categorization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Our results confirm the usefulness of the CSF Aβ42/40 ratio in the interpretation of CSF biomarker profiles in MCI patients, by increasing the proportion of conclusive profiles and enhancing their predictive value for underlying AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Aβ42/40 ratio; CSF biomarkers; Mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Reasoning A 55-year-old Man With Rapidly Progressive Dementia and Parkinsonism</title>
      <link>/website/publication/clinical-reasoning-a-55-year-old-man-with-rapidly-progressive-dementia-and-parkinsonism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/clinical-reasoning-a-55-year-old-man-with-rapidly-progressive-dementia-and-parkinsonism/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosopagnosia as the Presenting Symptom of Whipple Disease</title>
      <link>/website/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whipple disease is a rare, chronic multisystem infectious disease. The central nervous system (CNS) is secondarily involved in 43% of patients; 5% of patients have isolated or primary CNS involvement. The most frequent CNS symptoms are cognitive changes. Prosopagnosia is an inability to recognize familiar faces, in a person who does not have vision impairments or cognitive alterations. This relatively rare condition is usually related to vascular, traumatic, degenerative, or infectious lesions. We report a 54-year-old woman who presented subacutely with fever, headache, and seizures that led to a diagnosis of infectious meningoencephalitis. She improved temporarily on broad-spectrum antibiotics, but then developed a chronically evolving cognitive impairment with associative prosopagnosia as the major complaint. She had a history of sporadic abdominal pain and mild sacroiliac arthralgia. After a negative duodenal biopsy, we confirmed primary CNS Whipple disease by polymerase chain reaction and brain biopsy. We treated the patient with ceftriaxone for 15 days and then co-trimoxazole for 2 years. At 8-year follow-up, she had no further impairments, but continuing prosopagnosia. To our knowledge, this is the first description of isolated prosopagnosia in a patient with primary CNS Whipple disease. Because CNS Whipple disease can lead to serious, irreversible lesions if not promptly treated, clinicians must suspect the diagnosis, treat with long-term antibiotics, and follow patients carefully to prevent recurrence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biparietal Variant of Alzheimer&#39;s Disease - A Rare Presentation of a Common Disease</title>
      <link>/website/publication/biparietal-variant-of-alzheimers-disease-a-rare-presentation-of-a-common-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/biparietal-variant-of-alzheimers-disease-a-rare-presentation-of-a-common-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) is a clinically heterogeneous disease that may have atypical presentations with focal cortical syndromes and relatively preserved episodic memory. The posterior variant of AD has two subtypes: occipitotemporal, presenting with visuoperceptive impairment, and biparietal, presenting with visuospatial dysfunction and apraxia. We report a case of a 51-year-old woman with progressive limb apraxia and choreiform movements. Her neuropsychological evaluation was compatible with dementia, and revealed ideomotor and ideational limb apraxia, severe visuoconstructive ability impairment, dyscalculia and posterior aphasia. Workup excluded metabolic, infectious, inflammatory or neoplastic causes, and hereditary conditions as Huntington&amp;rsquo;s disease and familial AD. Cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers revealed β-amyloid reduction and τ protein increase. Brain imaging showed marked biparietal atrophy and hypoperfusion, and widespread cortical β-amyloid deposition. Biparietal variant of AD was diagnosed and acetylcholinesterase inhibitor treatment induced clinical stabilisation. AD may present with atypical features and a high clinical suspicion is necessary for an early diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
