<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/publication_types/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>/publication_types/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faster Cortical Thinning and Surface Area Loss in Presymptomatic and Symptomatic C9orf72 Repeat Expansion Adult Carriers</title>
      <link>/publication/faster-cortical-thinning-and-surface-area-loss-in-presymptomatic-and-symptomatic-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-adult-carriers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/faster-cortical-thinning-and-surface-area-loss-in-presymptomatic-and-symptomatic-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-adult-carriers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective: C9orf72 expansion is the most common genetic cause of frontotemporal dementia (FTD). We examined aging trajectories of cortical thickness (CTh) and surface area in C9orf72 expansion adult carriers compared to healthy controls to characterize preclinical cerebral changes leading to symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Data were obtained from the Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia Initiative. T1-weighted MRI scans were processed with CIVET 2.1 to extract vertex-wide CTh and CSA. Symptomatic and presymptomatic subjects were compared to age-matched controls using mixed-effects models, controlling for demographic variables. Aging trajectories were compared between carriers and non-carriers by testing the &amp;lsquo;age by genetic status&amp;rsquo; interaction. False-discovery rate corrections were applied to all vertex-wide analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The sample included 640 scans from 386 subjects, including 54 symptomatic C9orf72 carriers (72.2% behavioral variant FTD), 83 asymptomatic carriers and 249 controls (age range 18-86). Symptomatic carriers showed fairly symmetric reduction in CTh/CSA in most of the frontal lobes, in addition to large temporo-parietal areas. Presymptomatic subjects had reduced CTh/CSA in more restricted areas of the medial fronto-parietal lobes, in addition to scattered lateral fronto-parieto-temporal areas. These differences were explained by faster cortical thinning linearly throughout adulthood in a similar anatomical distribution, with differences emerging in the early 30s. CSA reduction was also faster in mutation carriers predominantly in the ventro-frontal regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation: C9orf72 mutation carriers have faster cortical thinning and surface loss throughout adulthood in regions that show atrophy in symptomatic subjects. This suggests that the pathogenic effects of the mutation lead to structural cerebral changes decades prior to symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuronal Pentraxin 2 - A Synapse-Derived CSF Biomarker in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/neuronal-pentraxin-2-a-synapse-derived-csf-biomarker-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/neuronal-pentraxin-2-a-synapse-derived-csf-biomarker-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Synapse dysfunction is emerging as an early pathological event in frontotemporal dementia (FTD), however biomarkers are lacking. We aimed to investigate the value of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) neuronal pentraxins (NPTXs), a family of proteins involved in homeostatic synapse plasticity, as novel biomarkers in genetic FTD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We included 106 presymptomatic and 54 symptomatic carriers of a pathogenic mutation in GRN, C9orf72 or MAPT, and 70 healthy non-carriers participating in the Genetic Frontotemporal dementia Initiative (GENFI), all of whom had at least one CSF sample. We measured CSF concentrations of NPTX2 using an in-house ELISA, and NPTX1 and NPTX receptor (NPTXR) by Western blot. We correlated NPTX2 with corresponding clinical and neuroimaging datasets as well as with CSF neurofilament light chain (NfL) using linear regression analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Symptomatic mutation carriers had lower NPTX2 concentrations (median 643 pg/mL, IQR (301-872)) than presymptomatic carriers (1003 pg/mL (624-1358), p&amp;lt;0.001) and non-carriers (990 pg/mL (597-1373), p&amp;lt;0.001) (corrected for age). Similar results were found for NPTX1 and NPTXR. Among mutation carriers, NPTX2 concentration correlated with several clinical disease severity measures, NfL and grey matter volume of the frontal, temporal and parietal lobes, insula and whole brain. NPTX2 predicted subsequent decline in phonemic verbal fluency and Clinical Dementia Rating scale plus FTD modules. In longitudinal CSF samples, available in 13 subjects, NPTX2 decreased around symptom onset and in the symptomatic stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: We conclude that NPTX2 is a promising synapse-derived disease progression biomarker in genetic FTD.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Headache Intensity Is Associated With Increased White Matter Lesion Burden in CADASIL Patients</title>
      <link>/publication/headache-intensity-is-associated-with-increased-white-matter-lesion-burden-in-cadasil-patients/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/headache-intensity-is-associated-with-increased-white-matter-lesion-burden-in-cadasil-patients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract
Objectives: Cerebral autosomal dominant arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy (CADASIL) is the most common hereditary cause of vascular dementia in adults. Migraine is a major symptom of the disease. We aimed to identify clinical and demographical features of the headache associated with increased cerebral lesion burden in a cohort of CADASIL patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Thirty-two patients with CADASIL were enrolled in this cross-sectional study. Demographics data, vascular risk factors and headache characteristics were collected through a structured questionnaire. MRI (3-T) was used to determine white matter hyperintensities burden evaluated by its volume (WMH-V).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Regression analysis showed that age (β = 1.266, 95%CI = [0.805, 1.726], p &amp;lt; 0.001), headache intensity (β = 5.143, 95%CI = [2.362, 7.924], p = 0.001) and female sex (β = 19.727, 95%CI = [8.750, 30.075], p = 0.001) were the main predictors of WMH-V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Age, female sex and headache intensity are associated with increased white matter lesion volume in CADASIL.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plasma Glial Fibrillary Acidic Protein Is Raised in Progranulin-Associated Frontotemporal Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/plasma-glial-fibrillary-acidic-protein-is-raised-in-progranulin-associated-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/plasma-glial-fibrillary-acidic-protein-is-raised-in-progranulin-associated-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract
Background: There are few validated fluid biomarkers in frontotemporal dementia (FTD). Glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) is a measure of astrogliosis, a known pathological process of FTD, but has yet to be explored as potential biomarker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Plasma GFAP and neurofilament light chain (NfL) concentration were measured in 469 individuals enrolled in the Genetic FTD Initiative: 114 C9orf72 expansion carriers (74 presymptomatic, 40 symptomatic), 119 GRN mutation carriers (88 presymptomatic, 31 symptomatic), 53 MAPT mutation carriers (34 presymptomatic, 19 symptomatic) and 183 non-carrier controls. Biomarker measures were compared between groups using linear regression models adjusted for age and sex with family membership included as random effect. Participants underwent standardised clinical assessments including the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration-Clinical Dementia Rating scale and MRI. Spearman&amp;rsquo;s correlation coefficient was used to investigate the relationship of plasma GFAP to clinical and imaging measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Plasma GFAP concentration was significantly increased in symptomatic GRN mutation carriers (adjusted mean difference from controls 192.3 pg/mL, 95% CI 126.5 to 445.6), but not in those with C9orf72 expansions (9.0, -61.3 to 54.6), MAPT mutations (12.7, -33.3 to 90.4) or the presymptomatic groups. GFAP concentration was significantly positively correlated with age in both controls and the majority of the disease groups, as well as with NfL concentration. In the presymptomatic period, higher GFAP concentrations were correlated with a lower cognitive score (MMSE) and lower brain volume, while in the symptomatic period, higher concentrations were associated with faster rates of atrophy in the temporal lobe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Raised GFAP concentrations appear to be unique to GRN-related FTD, with levels potentially increasing just prior to symptom onset, suggesting that GFAP may be an important marker of proximity to onset, and helpful for forthcoming therapeutic prevention trials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Age at Symptom Onset and Death and Disease Duration in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia - An International Retrospective Cohort Study</title>
      <link>/publication/age-at-symptom-onset-and-death-and-disease-duration-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/age-at-symptom-onset-and-death-and-disease-duration-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Frontotemporal dementia is a heterogenous neurodegenerative disorder, with about a third of cases being genetic. Most of this genetic component is accounted for by mutations in GRN, MAPT, and C9orf72. In this study, we aimed to complement previous phenotypic studies by doing an international study of age at symptom onset, age at death, and disease duration in individuals with mutations in GRN, MAPT, and C9orf72.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: In this international, retrospective cohort study, we collected data on age at symptom onset, age at death, and disease duration for patients with pathogenic mutations in the GRN and MAPT genes and pathological expansions in the C9orf72 gene through the Frontotemporal Dementia Prevention Initiative and from published papers. We used mixed effects models to explore differences in age at onset, age at death, and disease duration between genetic groups and individual mutations. We also assessed correlations between the age at onset and at death of each individual and the age at onset and at death of their parents and the mean age at onset and at death of their family members. Lastly, we used mixed effects models to investigate the extent to which variability in age at onset and at death could be accounted for by family membership and the specific mutation carried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: Data were available from 3403 individuals from 1492 families: 1433 with C9orf72 expansions (755 families), 1179 with GRN mutations (483 families, 130 different mutations), and 791 with MAPT mutations (254 families, 67 different mutations). Mean age at symptom onset and at death was 49·5 years (SD 10·0; onset) and 58·5 years (11·3; death) in the MAPT group, 58·2 years (9·8; onset) and 65·3 years (10·9; death) in the C9orf72 group, and 61·3 years (8·8; onset) and 68·8 years (9·7; death) in the GRN group. Mean disease duration was 6·4 years (SD 4·9) in the C9orf72 group, 7·1 years (3·9) in the GRN group, and 9·3 years (6·4) in the MAPT group. Individual age at onset and at death was significantly correlated with both parental age at onset and at death and with mean family age at onset and at death in all three groups, with a stronger correlation observed in the MAPT group (r=0·45 between individual and parental age at onset, r=0·63 between individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·58 between individual and parental age at death, and r=0·69 between individual and mean family age at death) than in either the C9orf72 group (r=0·32 individual and parental age at onset, r=0·36 individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·38 individual and parental age at death, and r=0·40 individual and mean family age at death) or the GRN group (r=0·22 individual and parental age at onset, r=0·18 individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·22 individual and parental age at death, and r=0·32 individual and mean family age at death). Modelling showed that the variability in age at onset and at death in the MAPT group was explained partly by the specific mutation (48%, 95% CI 35-62, for age at onset; 61%, 47-73, for age at death), and even more by family membership (66%, 56-75, for age at onset; 74%, 65-82, for age at death). In the GRN group, only 2% (0-10) of the variability of age at onset and 9% (3-21) of that of age of death was explained by the specific mutation, whereas 14% (9-22) of the variability of age at onset and 20% (12-30) of that of age at death was explained by family membership. In the C9orf72 group, family membership explained 17% (11-26) of the variability of age at onset and 19% (12-29) of that of age at death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation: Our study showed that age at symptom onset and at death of people with genetic frontotemporal dementia is influenced by genetic group and, particularly for MAPT mutations, by the specific mutation carried and by family membership. Although estimation of age at onset will be an important factor in future pre-symptomatic therapeutic trials for all three genetic groups, our study suggests that data from other members of the family will be particularly helpful only for individuals with MAPT mutations. Further work in identifying both genetic and environmental factors that modify phenotype in all groups will be important to improve such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funding: UK Medical Research Council, National Institute for Health Research, and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Society.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single Word Repetition Predicts Long-Term Outcome of Aphasia Caused by an Ischemic Stroke</title>
      <link>/publication/single-word-repetition-predicts-long-term-outcome-of-aphasia-caused-by-an-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/single-word-repetition-predicts-long-term-outcome-of-aphasia-caused-by-an-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: Better understanding of clinical predictors of aphasia outcome is of the utmost importance, in patients&amp;rsquo; rehabilitation planning, expectation management, and further physiopathology understanding. We aimed to identify clinical predictors of long-term poststroke aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We conducted a prospective longitudinal observation study of patients with left-Middle Cerebral Artery stroke with aphasia. Patients were evaluated at baseline, day 7 and 6 months with National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) and Aphasia Rapid Test Other demographic variables and vascular risk factors were collected. A linear regression was performed to identify best predictors of aphasia at 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: We included 113 patients with a left hemisphere stroke, with 81 reaching the final evaluation. Aphasia Handicap Score at 6 months was predicted by baseline total NIHSS (β = .077, 95%CI = [.026, .127]. P = .004), infarct volume on CT-scan (β = .009, 95%CI = [.003, .015]. P = .003), single word repetition at baseline (β = .188, 95%CI = [.040, .335]. P = .013), and infection during hospitalization (β = .759, 95%CI = [.263, 1.255]. P = .003).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome in patients with stroke is predicted by a single word repetition task at baseline. Infection during hospitalization has a negative impact on aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome at 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lower CSF Amyloid-Beta 1-42 Predicts a Higher Mortality Rate in Frontotemporal Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/lower-csf-amyloid-beta-1-42-predicts-a-higher-mortality-rate-in-ftd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/lower-csf-amyloid-beta-1-42-predicts-a-higher-mortality-rate-in-ftd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frontotemporal lobar degeneration, the neuropathological substrate of frontotemporal dementia (FTD), is characterized by the deposition of protein aggregates, including tau. Evidence has shown concomitant amyloid pathology in some of these patients, which seems to contribute to a more aggressive disease. Our aim was to evaluate cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) amyloid-beta as a predictor of the mortality of FTD patients. We included 99 patients diagnosed with FTD-both behavioral and language variants-with no associated motor neuron disease, from whom a CSF sample was collected. These patients were followed prospectively in our center, and demographic and clinical data were obtained. The survival analysis was carried through a Cox regression model. Patients who died during follow up had a significantly lower CSF amyloid-beta1-42 than those who did not. The survival analysis demonstrated that an increased death rate was associated with a lower CSF amyloid-beta1-42 (HR = 0.999, 95% CI = [0.997, 1.000], p = 0.049). Neither demographic nor clinical variables, nor CSF total tau or p-tau were significantly associated with this endpoint. These results suggest that amyloid deposition in FTD patients may be associated with a higher mortality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serum Neurofilament Light Chain in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia - A Longitudinal, Multicentre Cohort Study</title>
      <link>/publication/serum-neurofilament-light-chain-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia-a-longitudinal-multicentre-cohort-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/serum-neurofilament-light-chain-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia-a-longitudinal-multicentre-cohort-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Neurofilament light chain (NfL) is a promising blood biomarker in genetic frontotemporal dementia, with elevated concentrations in symptomatic carriers of mutations in GRN, C9orf72, and MAPT. A better understanding of NfL dynamics is essential for upcoming therapeutic trials. We aimed to study longitudinal NfL trajectories in people with presymptomatic and symptomatic genetic frontotemporal dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We recruited participants from 14 centres collaborating in the Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia Initiative (GENFI), which is a multicentre cohort study of families with genetic frontotemporal dementia done across Europe and Canada. Eligible participants (aged ≥18 years) either had frontotemporal dementia due to a pathogenic mutation in GRN, C9orf72, or MAPT (symptomatic mutation carriers) or were healthy at-risk first-degree relatives (either presymptomatic mutation carriers or non-carriers), and had at least two serum samples with a time interval of 6 months or more. Participants were excluded if they had neurological comorbidities that were likely to affect NfL, including cerebrovascular events. We measured NfL longitudinally in serum samples collected between June 8, 2012, and Dec 8, 2017, through follow-up visits annually or every 2 years, which also included MRI and neuropsychological assessments. Using mixed-effects models, we analysed NfL changes over time and correlated them with longitudinal imaging and clinical parameters, controlling for age, sex, and study site. The primary outcome was the course of NfL over time in the various stages of genetic frontotemporal dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: We included 59 symptomatic carriers and 149 presymptomatic carriers of a mutation in GRN, C9orf72, or MAPT, and 127 non-carriers. Nine presymptomatic carriers became symptomatic during follow-up (so-called converters). Baseline NfL was elevated in symptomatic carriers (median 52 pg/mL [IQR 24-69]) compared with presymptomatic carriers (9 pg/mL [6-13]; p&amp;lt;0·0001) and non-carriers (8 pg/mL [6-11]; p&amp;lt;0·0001), and was higher in converters than in non-converting carriers (19 pg/mL [17-28] vs 8 pg/mL [6-11]; p=0·0007; adjusted for age). During follow-up, NfL increased in converters (b=0·097 [SE 0·018]; p&amp;lt;0·0001). In symptomatic mutation carriers overall, NfL did not change during follow-up (b=0·017 [SE 0·010]; p=0·101) and remained elevated. Rates of NfL change over time were associated with rate of decline in Mini Mental State Examination (b=-94·7 [SE 33·9]; p=0·003) and atrophy rate in several grey matter regions, but not with change in Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration-Clinical Dementia Rating scale score (b=-3·46 [SE 46·3]; p=0·941).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation: Our findings show the value of blood NfL as a disease progression biomarker in genetic frontotemporal dementia and suggest that longitudinal NfL measurements could identify mutation carriers approaching symptom onset and capture rates of brain atrophy. The characterisation of NfL over the course of disease provides valuable information for its use as a treatment effect marker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funding: ZonMw and the Bluefield project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminative Capacity and Construct Validity of the Clock Drawing Test in Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: The aim of this study was to analyze the psychometric and diagnostic properties of the Clock Drawing Test (CDT), scored according to the Babins, Rouleau, and Cahn scoring systems, for Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) screening, and develop corresponding cutoff scores. Additionally, we assessed the construct validity of the CDT through exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis. 
Methods: We developed a cross-sectional study of ambulatory MCI and AD patients, divided in two clinical groups (450 MCI and 250 mild AD patients) and a normal control group (N = 400). All participants were assessed with the CDT, Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) for convergent validity. 
Results: The selected scoring systems presented adequate validity and reliability values. The proposed cutoff scores showed 60 to 65% sensitivity and 58 to 62% specificity to identify MCI patients. The corresponding values for AD were 84 to 90% sensitivity and 76 to 78% specificity. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis revealed that the Babins scoring system had good construct validity and allowed us to propose a three-factor model for this system. 
Conclusions: Our results confirmed the complexity of the CDT and support it as a cognitive screening instrument particularly sensitive to AD. The use of the CDT with MCI patients should be interpreted with more caution due to the lower sensitivity and specificity for milder forms of cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Mild Cognitive Impairment; Neuropsychological tests; cognitive screening; confirmatory factor analysis; exploratory factor analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education Modulates Brain Maintenance in Presymptomatic Frontotemporal Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/education-modulates-brain-maintenance-in-presymptomatic-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/education-modulates-brain-maintenance-in-presymptomatic-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective: Cognitively engaging lifestyles have been associated with reduced risk of conversion to dementia. Multiple mechanisms have been advocated, including increased brain volumes (ie, brain reserve) and reduced disease progression (ie, brain maintenance). In cross-sectional studies of presymptomatic frontotemporal dementia (FTD), higher education has been related to increased grey matter volume. Here, we examine the effect of education on grey matter loss over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Two-hundred twenty-nine subjects at-risk of carrying a pathogenic mutation leading to FTD underwent longitudinal cognitive assessment and T1-weighted MRI at baseline and at 1 year follow-up. The first principal component score of the graph-Laplacian Principal Component Analysis on 112 grey matter region-of-interest volumes was used to summarise the grey matter volume (GMV). The effects of education on cognitive performances and GMV at baseline and on the change between 1 year follow-up and baseline (slope) were tested by Structural Equation Modelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Highly educated at-risk subjects had better cognition and higher grey matter volume at baseline; moreover, higher educational attainment was associated with slower loss of grey matter over time in mutation carriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: This longitudinal study demonstrates that even in presence of ongoing pathological processes, education may facilitate both brain reserve and brain maintenance in the presymptomatic phase of genetic FTD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: brain maintenance; brain reserve; frontotemporal dementia (FTD); graph theory; magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Increased CSF Tau Is Associated With a Higher Risk of Seizures in Patients With Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/increased-csf-tau-is-associated-with-a-higher-risk-of-seizures-in-patients-with-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/increased-csf-tau-is-associated-with-a-higher-risk-of-seizures-in-patients-with-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Neurofibrillary tangles and tau protein, the neuropathological hallmarks of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD), have been identified in patients with epilepsy. Tau protein was also associated with the modulation of neuronal excitability in animal models of AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Materials and methods: We evaluated in 292 patients with AD the association between the risk of seizure development and AD cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers, demographic characteristics, baseline Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score, comorbidities, and apolipoprotein E status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The development of seizures was associated with younger age at dementia&amp;rsquo;s onset, lower baseline MMSE, and higher CSF total tau protein levels, but only MMSE (hazard ratio [HR] = 0.935; 95% confidence interval [CI] = [0.903, 0.968]; p &amp;lt; 0.001) and CSF tau (HR = 1.001; 95%CI = [1.001, 1.002]; p = 0.001) were independent predictors on multivariate analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: While CSF tau and lower baseline MMSE association with seizure development could in part be explained by a greater degree of cortical damage, the role of tau in the modulation of neuronal excitability may also play a role and should be further investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer; Biomarkers; CSF; Epilepsy; Seizure; Tau.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Network Resilience to Pathology in Presymptomatic Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia decline presymptomatically</title>
      <link>/publication/functional-network-resilience-to-pathology-in-presymptomatic-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/functional-network-resilience-to-pathology-in-presymptomatic-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presymptomatic phase of neurodegenerative diseases are characterized by structural brain changes without significant clinical features. We set out to investigate the contribution of functional network resilience to preserved cognition in presymptomatic genetic frontotemporal dementia. We studied 172 people from families carrying genetic abnormalities in C9orf72, MAPT, or PGRN. Networks were extracted from functional MRI data and assessed using graph theoretical analysis. We found that despite loss of both brain volume and functional connections, there is maintenance of an efficient topological organization of the brain&amp;rsquo;s functional network in the years leading up to the estimated age of frontotemporal dementia symptom onset. After this point, functional network efficiency declines markedly. Reduction in connectedness was most marked in highly connected hub regions. Measures of topological efficiency of the brain&amp;rsquo;s functional network and organization predicted cognitive dysfunction in domains related to symptomatic frontotemporal dementia and connectivity correlated with brain volume loss in frontotemporal dementia. We propose that maintaining the efficient organization of the brain&amp;rsquo;s functional network supports cognitive health even as atrophy and connectivity decline presymptomatically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Inner Fluctuations of the Brain in Presymptomatic Frontotemporal Dementia - The Chronnectome Fingerprint</title>
      <link>/publication/the-inner-fluctuations-of-the-brain-in-presymptomatic-frontotemporal-dementia-the-chronnectome-fingerprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/the-inner-fluctuations-of-the-brain-in-presymptomatic-frontotemporal-dementia-the-chronnectome-fingerprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frontotemporal Dementia (FTD) is preceded by a long period of subtle brain changes, occurring in the absence of overt cognitive symptoms, that need to be still fully characterized. Dynamic network analysis based on resting-state magnetic resonance imaging (rs-fMRI) is a potentially powerful tool for the study of preclinical FTD. In the present study, we employed a &amp;ldquo;chronnectome&amp;rdquo; approach (recurring, time-varying patterns of connectivity) to evaluate measures of dynamic connectivity in 472 at-risk FTD subjects from the Genetic Frontotemporal dementia research Initiative (GENFI) cohort. We considered 249 subjects with FTD-related pathogenetic mutations and 223 mutation non-carriers (HC). Dynamic connectivity was evaluated using independent component analysis and sliding-time window correlation to rs-fMRI data, and meta-state measures of global brain flexibility were extracted. Results show that presymptomatic FTD exhibits diminished dynamic fluidity, visiting less meta-states, shifting less often across them, and travelling through a narrowed meta-state distance, as compared to HC. Dynamic connectivity changes characterize preclinical FTD, arguing for the desynchronization of the inner fluctuations of the brain. These changes antedate clinical symptoms, and might represent an early signature of FTD to be used as a biomarker in clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: C9orf72; Chronnectome; Dynamic brain functional connectivity; Frontotemporal dementia; Granulin; Microtuble associate protein tau; Mutation; resting-state fMRI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Increased Risk of Melanoma in C9ORF72 Repeat Expansion Carriers - A Case-Control Study</title>
      <link>/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) are considered part of the same pathological spectrum. There is an increased risk of ALS in patients who have had melanoma. The risk of FTLD in melanoma (or cancer) patients is unknown. We aimed to study if C9ORF72 expansion is linked to a higher prevalence of melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We selected patients with a diagnosis in the ALS-FTLD spectrum who were tested for pathogenic mutations. Medical history was reviewed, to identify those with pathologically documented melanomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: We included 189 patients. Sixty-two had identified pathogenic mutations (39 C9ORF72). C9ORF72 carriers had a significantly higher risk of melanoma (odds ratio = 24.709; P &amp;lt; 0.007). There was no association with phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: These findings suggest that patients with a history of melanoma may have an increased probability of carrying a C9ORF72 repeat expansion. ALS or FTLD carriers of C9ORF72 should undergo surveillance for skin changes. Muscle Nerve 59:362-365, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: C9ORF72; amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; frontotemporal dementia; melanoma; skin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intracranial Internal Carotid Artery Wall Calcification in Ischemic Strokes Treated With Thrombolysis</title>
      <link>/publication/intracranial-internal-carotid-artery-wall-calcification-in-ischemic-strokes-treated-with-thrombolysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/intracranial-internal-carotid-artery-wall-calcification-in-ischemic-strokes-treated-with-thrombolysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Calcifications are an important element of atherosclerotic plaques and have been used as a marker of atherosclerosis and clinical outcome predictor in different vascular territories. CT-scan, performed in the acute ischemic stroke setting, can reliably detect intracranial arterial calcifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: To investigate the association between intracranial internal carotid artery calcification and functional outcome, symptomatic intracerebral hemorrhage (sICH), recanalization, and death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We included 396 consecutive ischemic stroke patients submitted to recombinant tissue plasminogen activator treatment between January 2011 and September 2014. Admission CT-scans were reviewed to calculate the Total Carotid Syphon Calcification score. Patients were followed for up to at least 6 months post-stroke or until death. Outcome measures included evaluation of recanalization on the first 24 h (transcranial color coded Doppler or angio-CT), sICH, and assessment of functional outcome at 3 months after stroke (using modified Rankin scale).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Carotid artery wall calcification did not predict sICH, recanalization or any good outcome. However, it was a statistically significant predictor of death (OR 1.102, 95% CI [1.004-1.211], p = 0.042).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Intracranial carotid artery calcification does not increase the risk of thrombolysis-induced sICH. Patients with higher grade of carotid artery wall calcification may have a higher mortality rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Calcification; Carotid; Hemorrhage; Outcome; Stroke; Thrombolysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Head Turning Sign in Dementia and Mild Cognitive Impairment - Its Relationship to Cognition, Behavior, and Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarkers</title>
      <link>/publication/the-head-turning-sign-in-dementia-and-mild-cognitive-impairment-its-relationship-to-cognition-behavior-and-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarkers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/the-head-turning-sign-in-dementia-and-mild-cognitive-impairment-its-relationship-to-cognition-behavior-and-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarkers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background/aims: The head turning sign (HTS) is frequently noticed in clinical practice, but few studies have investigated its etiological and neuropsychological correlates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: The presence and frequency of the HTS was operationalized and prospectively evaluated in patients with Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD), amnestic mild cognitive impairment (MCI), and behavioral-variant frontotemporal dementia (bvFTD). Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) samples for AD biomarkers were collected. Mini-Mental State Examination, Montreal Cognitive Assessment, Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS), and insight scale scores were ascertained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: A total of 84 patients were included. The HTS was more prevalent in AD than in MCI or bvFTD. It correlated negatively with cognitive measures and depression. It also had a positive correlation with CSF total tau and hyperphosphorylated tau proteins. Total tau protein and GDS score were the only variables independently associated with the HTS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: The presence of the HTS in a cognitively impaired individual suggests a diagnosis of AD. A higher HTS frequency correlates with higher CSF total tau levels, a smaller GDS score, and worse cognitive measures. In the MCI subgroup, the HTS may suggest a higher risk of progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers; Clinical diagnosis; Frontotemporal dementia; Head turning sign; Mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Classical aphasia evaluation scales are too long to use in the context of acute stroke or as a monitoring tool. The Aphasia Rapid Test is a 26-point scale developed as a bedside assessment to rate aphasia severity in acute stroke patients in less than 3 minutes. We aimed to adapt and validate this scale for European Portuguese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: We evaluated 56 acute stroke patients in the first and in the seventh days post-stroke. In the seventh day, patients were evaluated by two independent raters, to evaluate inter-rater agreement. To study concurrent validity, the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was applied to a subset of 20 patients. The predictive ability of the Aphasia Rapid Test was assessed at six months, by the aphasia subscale of the National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Translation to European Portuguese was based in the French and English versions, considering the words&amp;rsquo; utilization frequency. The Chronbach&amp;rsquo;s alpha was 0.796. The concordance coefficient between the two raters was excellent (0.985). Correlation between Aphasia Rapid Test and the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was strong (r = -0.958, p &amp;lt; 0.001). The study through Bland-Altman graphs corroborated the good inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity of the test. The Aphasia Rapid Test score in the first day is an independent predictor of long-term outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: This study provides reliable results for European Portuguese, with adequate internal consistency, inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: The Aphasia Rapid Test is a good tool for the evaluation and monitoring of aphasia in stroke patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validity and Clinical Utility of Different Clock Drawing Test Scoring Systems in Multiple Forms of Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clock Drawing Test (CDT) has a known potential for the detection of cognitive impairment in populations with dementia, especially Alzheimer disease (AD). Our aim was to compare the clinical utility of 3 CDT scoring systems (Rouleau, Cahn, and Babins) in several pathologies with cognitive compromise from a tertiary center memory clinic. We selected patients with a clinical diagnosis of mild stage AD, behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia (FTD), vascular dementia (VaD), dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB), and Parkinson disease with dementia (PDD). The results showed significant differences between the several diagnoses with the following pattern of results: AD, DLB &amp;lt; FTD, VaD, PDD. Qualitative analysis of clock drawing errors confirmed the stimulus-bound response as a hallmark of AD, while conceptual deficit was significantly more prevalent in patients with AD and DLB. Our results supported the CDT potential as a cognitive screening measure for mild dementia, particularly sensitive to AD and DLB, especially when we used the Cahn scoring system and its analysis of qualitative errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: cognitive screening; dementia; neuropsychological tests; validation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addition of the Aβ42/40 Ratio to the Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarker Profile Increases the Predictive Value for Underlying Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Dementia in Mild Cognitive Impairment</title>
      <link>/publication/addition-of-the-a%CE%B24240-ratio-to-the-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarker-profile-increases-the-predictive-value-for-underlying-alzheimers-disease-dementia-in-mild-cognitive-impairment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/addition-of-the-a%CE%B24240-ratio-to-the-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarker-profile-increases-the-predictive-value-for-underlying-alzheimers-disease-dementia-in-mild-cognitive-impairment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers have been used to increase the evidence of underlying Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) pathology in mild cognitive impairment (MCI). However, CSF biomarker-based classification often results in conflicting profiles with controversial prognostic value. Normalization of the CSF Aβ42 concentration to the level of total amyloid beta (Aβ), using the Aβ42/40 ratio, has been shown to improve the distinction between AD and non-AD dementia. Therefore, we evaluated whether the Aβ42/40 ratio would improve MCI categorization and more accurately predict progression to AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Our baseline population consisted of 197 MCI patients, of which 144 had a follow-up ≥ 2 years, and comprised the longitudinal study group. To establish our own CSF Aβ42/40 ratio reference value, a group of 168 AD-dementia patients and 66 neurological controls was also included. CSF biomarker-based classification was operationalized according to the framework of the National Institute of Aging-Alzheimer Association criteria for MCI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: When using the core CSF biomarkers (Aβ42, total Tau and phosphorylated Tau), 30% of the patients fell into the high-AD-likelihood (HL) group (both amyloid and neurodegeneration markers positive), 30% into the low-AD-likelihood group (all biomarkers negative), 28% into the suspected non-Alzheimer pathophysiology (SNAP) group (only neurodegeneration markers positive) and 12% into the isolated amyloid pathology group (only amyloid-positive). Replacing Aβ42 by the Aβ42/40 ratio resulted in a significant increase in the percentage of patients with amyloidosis (42-59%) and in the proportion of interpretable biological profiles (61-75%), due to a reduction by half in the number of SNAP cases and an increase in the proportion of the HL subgroup. Survival analysis showed that risk of progression to AD was highest in the HL group, and increased when the Aβ42/40 ratio, instead of Aβ42, combined with total Tau and phosphorylated Tau was used for biomarker-based categorization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Our results confirm the usefulness of the CSF Aβ42/40 ratio in the interpretation of CSF biomarker profiles in MCI patients, by increasing the proportion of conclusive profiles and enhancing their predictive value for underlying AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Aβ42/40 ratio; CSF biomarkers; Mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog) - Normative Data for the Portuguese Population</title>
      <link>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale is a brief battery developed to assess cognitive functioning in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease that encompasses the core characteristics of cognitive decline (e.g. memory, language, praxis, constructive ability and orientation). The early detection, as well as the monitoring of cognitive decline along disease progression, is extremely important in clinical care and interventional research. The main goals of the present study were to analyze the psychometric properties of the Portuguese version of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale, and to establish normative values for the Portuguese population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: The Portuguese version of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was administered to 223 cognitively healthy participants according to a standard assessment protocol consisting of the Mini-Mental State Examination, the Montreal Cognitive Assessment and the Adults and Older Adults Functional Assessment Inventory. Normal performance on the assessment protocol was the inclusion criteria for the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale revealed good psychometric properties when used in the Portuguese population. Age was the main predictor of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total score (R2 = 0.123), whereas the influence of education level was lower (R2 = 0.027). These two variables explained 14.4% of the variance on the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale scores and were used to stratify the normative values for the Portuguese population presented here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: On the total sample, the average total score in the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was 6 points. The normative data were determined according to age and educational level as these were the sociodemographic variables that significantly contributed to the prediction of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total scores, explaining 14.4% of their variance. The normative data are of the utmost importance to ensure proper use of this battery in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer Disease; Cognitive Dysfunction; Neuropsychological Tests; Portugal; Surveys and Questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neurosonology Accuracy for Isolated Acute Vestibular Syndromes</title>
      <link>/publication/neurosonology-accuracy-for-isolated-acute-vestibular-syndromes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/neurosonology-accuracy-for-isolated-acute-vestibular-syndromes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: The clinical approach to acute vestibular syndromes is often complex for the physician. Neurosonology offers a noninvasive method to study the cervicocephalic circulation when a vascular etiology is suspected. We aim to evaluate the diagnostic accuracy of a vascular neurosonological exam in isolated acute vestibular syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: All patients submitted to cerebrovascular ultrasound and magnetic resonance imaging during the period between 2011 and 2015 with acute isolated vestibular syndrome. Those with any clinical sign of brainstem lesion on presentation were excluded. All patients performed the neuroimaging study (brain computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging) and neurologic surveillance. Neurosonological exam included all intra- and extracranial segments of the vertebrobasilar circulation. Positive ultrasound exam was defined as the presence of stenotic or occlusive disease in any of these segments related to the infarcted area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: A total of 108 patients were included: 60 (53.6%) were males (mean age: 60.75 years (standard deviation, 14.17)). In 27 patients (25.0%) a cerebral ischemic lesion was found to be the cause of the vertigo. Neurosonological assessment showed a sensitivity of 40.7% (95% confidence interval (CI): 22.4; 61.2), specificity of 100% (95% CI: 95.5; 100.0), positive predictive value (PPV) of 100% (95% CI: 71.5; 100.0), and negative predictive value (NPV) of 83.5% (95% CI: 74.6; 90.3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Our study suggests that cerebrovascular ultrasound is a highly specific method for the diagnosis of cerebrovascular vertigo. However, its low sensitivity makes it a poor candidate for screening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: neurosonology; stroke; ultrasound; vertigo; vestibular.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Reasoning A 55-year-old Man With Rapidly Progressive Dementia and Parkinsonism</title>
      <link>/publication/clinical-reasoning-a-55-year-old-man-with-rapidly-progressive-dementia-and-parkinsonism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/clinical-reasoning-a-55-year-old-man-with-rapidly-progressive-dementia-and-parkinsonism/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>European Academy of Neurology - Resident and Research Fellow Section - Innovations and Future Direction in 2017</title>
      <link>/publication/european-academy-of-neurology-resident-and-research-fellow-section-innovations-and-future-direction-in-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/european-academy-of-neurology-resident-and-research-fellow-section-innovations-and-future-direction-in-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Association Between Butyrylcholinesterase and Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarkers in Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Patients</title>
      <link>/publication/association-between-butyrylcholinesterase-and-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarkers-in-alzheimers-disease-patients/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/association-between-butyrylcholinesterase-and-cerebrospinal-fluid-biomarkers-in-alzheimers-disease-patients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deficit of cholinergic activity is one of the main findings in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD), and is related to the synthesis of acetylcholine, and the hydrolysing enzymes, acetylcholinesterase and butyrylcholinesterase (BuChE). Together with the Apolipoprotein E-ε4 allele (ApoE-ε4), the BuChE-K variant has been proposed to increase AD risk in certain populations. In addition, this polymorphism has been associated with a lower capacity to attenuate β-amyloid aggregation. In the present study we explored the interaction of the BuChE-K variant with its activity in CSF, conventional AD biomarkers and ApoE genotype. 217 AD patients and 200 age-matched controls were genotyped for the ApoE and the BuChE-K variant. BuChE activity in CSF, as well as the levels of the CSF-AD biomarkers amyloid-beta 42 (Aβ42), total and hyperphosphorylated tau (t-tau and p-tau) were determined in 88 of these patients. The results showed no significant differences in the BuChE-K variant distribution between patients and controls. No influence of the BuChE-K variant was seen neither in CSF BuChE activity, nor in the levels of Aβ42, t-tau and p-tau in AD patients. ApoE genotype also did not seem to influence CSF BuChE activity. Interestingly, in AD patients, an association between high CSF BuChE activity and increased levels of CSF Aβ42 was shown, particularly in ApoE-ε4 allele carriers. In our population, the BuChE-K variant does not seem to confer risk for AD or to influence the activity of the enzyme in CSF. However, we demonstrated an association between BuChE activity, ApoE-ε4 genotype and CSF Aβ42 levels, highlighting the importance of assessing BuChE activity as a possible modulator of Aβ load in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimeŕs disease; Amyloid-beta 42; Apolipoprotein E; Butyrylcholinesterase; Cerebrospinal fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tremor Frequency Assessment by iPhone® Applications - Correlation With EMG Analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/tremor-frequency-assessment-by-iphone-applications-correlation-with-emg-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/tremor-frequency-assessment-by-iphone-applications-correlation-with-emg-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tremor frequency analysis is usually performed by EMG studies but accelerometers are progressively being more used. The iPhone® contains an accelerometer and many applications claim to be capable of measuring tremor frequency. We tested three applications in twenty-two patients with a diagnosis of PD, ET and Holmes&amp;rsquo; tremor. EMG needle assessment as well as accelerometry was performed at the same time. There was very strong correlation (Pearson &amp;gt;0.8, p &amp;lt; 0.001) between the three applications, the EMG needle and the accelerometry. Our data suggests the apps LiftPulse®, iSeismometer® and Studymytremor® are a reliable alternative to the EMG for tremor frequency assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: EMG; Tremor; accelerometers; frequency; iPhone; smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosopagnosia as the Presenting Symptom of Whipple Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whipple disease is a rare, chronic multisystem infectious disease. The central nervous system (CNS) is secondarily involved in 43% of patients; 5% of patients have isolated or primary CNS involvement. The most frequent CNS symptoms are cognitive changes. Prosopagnosia is an inability to recognize familiar faces, in a person who does not have vision impairments or cognitive alterations. This relatively rare condition is usually related to vascular, traumatic, degenerative, or infectious lesions. We report a 54-year-old woman who presented subacutely with fever, headache, and seizures that led to a diagnosis of infectious meningoencephalitis. She improved temporarily on broad-spectrum antibiotics, but then developed a chronically evolving cognitive impairment with associative prosopagnosia as the major complaint. She had a history of sporadic abdominal pain and mild sacroiliac arthralgia. After a negative duodenal biopsy, we confirmed primary CNS Whipple disease by polymerase chain reaction and brain biopsy. We treated the patient with ceftriaxone for 15 days and then co-trimoxazole for 2 years. At 8-year follow-up, she had no further impairments, but continuing prosopagnosia. To our knowledge, this is the first description of isolated prosopagnosia in a patient with primary CNS Whipple disease. Because CNS Whipple disease can lead to serious, irreversible lesions if not promptly treated, clinicians must suspect the diagnosis, treat with long-term antibiotics, and follow patients carefully to prevent recurrence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prognosis of Early-Onset vs. Late-Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment -  Comparison of Conversion Rates and Its Predictors</title>
      <link>/publication/prognosis-of-early-onset-vs.-late-onset-mild-cognitive-impairment-comparison-of-conversion-rates-and-its-predictors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/prognosis-of-early-onset-vs.-late-onset-mild-cognitive-impairment-comparison-of-conversion-rates-and-its-predictors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Despite having the same histopathological characteristics, early-onset and late-onset Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) patients show some distinct clinical and neuropsychological profiles. Early Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment (EOMCI) is a less characterized group. The aim of this study is to characterize MCI probably due to AD in terms of the clinical, genetic, Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers profile and conversion rate of EOMCI, compared to the late-onset form (LOMCI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: 159 MCI patients were divided in two groups: 52 EOMCI (onset &amp;lt; 65 years) and 107 LOMCI (onset ≥ 65 years). We investigated differences in neuropsychological scores, clinical variables, ApoE genotype, CSF biomarkers (Aβ42, t-Tau and p-Tau) in both groups. Conversion was ascertained during follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: EOMCI showed a longer duration of symptoms prior to the first evaluation (EOMCI = 4.57 vs. LOMCI = 3.31, p = 0.008) and scored higher on the subjective memory complaints scale (9.91 vs. 7.85, p = 0.008), but performed better in brief cognitive tests (27.81 vs. 26.51, p &amp;lt; 0.001 in Mini-Mental State Examination; 19.84 vs. 18.67, p = 0.005 in Montreal Cognitive Assessment) than LOMCI. ApoE genotype distribution and CSF biomarker profile were similar in both groups, as was the conversion risk. Lower Aβ42 (Hazard ratio (HR): 0.998, 95% Confidence Interval (CI) = [0.996⁻1.000], p = 0.042), higher t-Tau levels (HR: 1.003, 95%CI = [1.000⁻1.005], p = 0.039) and higher scores in the Alzheimer Disease Assessment Scale-Cognitive (HR: 1.186, 95%CI = [1.083⁻1.299], p = 0.002) increased the risk of conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Despite differences in memory performance and memory complaints, EOMCI and LOMCI seem to represent indistinct biological groups that do not have a higher risk of conversion to AD or differ in risk factors for conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer; MCI; biomarkers; conversion; dementia; early-onset; late-onset; mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biparietal Variant of Alzheimer&#39;s Disease - A Rare Presentation of a Common Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/biparietal-variant-of-alzheimers-disease-a-rare-presentation-of-a-common-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/biparietal-variant-of-alzheimers-disease-a-rare-presentation-of-a-common-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) is a clinically heterogeneous disease that may have atypical presentations with focal cortical syndromes and relatively preserved episodic memory. The posterior variant of AD has two subtypes: occipitotemporal, presenting with visuoperceptive impairment, and biparietal, presenting with visuospatial dysfunction and apraxia. We report a case of a 51-year-old woman with progressive limb apraxia and choreiform movements. Her neuropsychological evaluation was compatible with dementia, and revealed ideomotor and ideational limb apraxia, severe visuoconstructive ability impairment, dyscalculia and posterior aphasia. Workup excluded metabolic, infectious, inflammatory or neoplastic causes, and hereditary conditions as Huntington&amp;rsquo;s disease and familial AD. Cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers revealed β-amyloid reduction and τ protein increase. Brain imaging showed marked biparietal atrophy and hypoperfusion, and widespread cortical β-amyloid deposition. Biparietal variant of AD was diagnosed and acetylcholinesterase inhibitor treatment induced clinical stabilisation. AD may present with atypical features and a high clinical suspicion is necessary for an early diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
