<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>c9orf72 | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/tags/c9orf72/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/tags/c9orf72/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>c9orf72</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>c9orf72</title>
      <link>/website/tags/c9orf72/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faster Cortical Thinning and Surface Area Loss in Presymptomatic and Symptomatic C9orf72 Repeat Expansion Adult Carriers</title>
      <link>/website/publication/faster-cortical-thinning-and-surface-area-loss-in-presymptomatic-and-symptomatic-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-adult-carriers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/faster-cortical-thinning-and-surface-area-loss-in-presymptomatic-and-symptomatic-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-adult-carriers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective: C9orf72 expansion is the most common genetic cause of frontotemporal dementia (FTD). We examined aging trajectories of cortical thickness (CTh) and surface area in C9orf72 expansion adult carriers compared to healthy controls to characterize preclinical cerebral changes leading to symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Data were obtained from the Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia Initiative. T1-weighted MRI scans were processed with CIVET 2.1 to extract vertex-wide CTh and CSA. Symptomatic and presymptomatic subjects were compared to age-matched controls using mixed-effects models, controlling for demographic variables. Aging trajectories were compared between carriers and non-carriers by testing the &amp;lsquo;age by genetic status&amp;rsquo; interaction. False-discovery rate corrections were applied to all vertex-wide analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The sample included 640 scans from 386 subjects, including 54 symptomatic C9orf72 carriers (72.2% behavioral variant FTD), 83 asymptomatic carriers and 249 controls (age range 18-86). Symptomatic carriers showed fairly symmetric reduction in CTh/CSA in most of the frontal lobes, in addition to large temporo-parietal areas. Presymptomatic subjects had reduced CTh/CSA in more restricted areas of the medial fronto-parietal lobes, in addition to scattered lateral fronto-parieto-temporal areas. These differences were explained by faster cortical thinning linearly throughout adulthood in a similar anatomical distribution, with differences emerging in the early 30s. CSA reduction was also faster in mutation carriers predominantly in the ventro-frontal regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation: C9orf72 mutation carriers have faster cortical thinning and surface loss throughout adulthood in regions that show atrophy in symptomatic subjects. This suggests that the pathogenic effects of the mutation lead to structural cerebral changes decades prior to symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Age at Symptom Onset and Death and Disease Duration in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia - An International Retrospective Cohort Study</title>
      <link>/website/publication/age-at-symptom-onset-and-death-and-disease-duration-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/age-at-symptom-onset-and-death-and-disease-duration-in-genetic-frontotemporal-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Frontotemporal dementia is a heterogenous neurodegenerative disorder, with about a third of cases being genetic. Most of this genetic component is accounted for by mutations in GRN, MAPT, and C9orf72. In this study, we aimed to complement previous phenotypic studies by doing an international study of age at symptom onset, age at death, and disease duration in individuals with mutations in GRN, MAPT, and C9orf72.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: In this international, retrospective cohort study, we collected data on age at symptom onset, age at death, and disease duration for patients with pathogenic mutations in the GRN and MAPT genes and pathological expansions in the C9orf72 gene through the Frontotemporal Dementia Prevention Initiative and from published papers. We used mixed effects models to explore differences in age at onset, age at death, and disease duration between genetic groups and individual mutations. We also assessed correlations between the age at onset and at death of each individual and the age at onset and at death of their parents and the mean age at onset and at death of their family members. Lastly, we used mixed effects models to investigate the extent to which variability in age at onset and at death could be accounted for by family membership and the specific mutation carried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: Data were available from 3403 individuals from 1492 families: 1433 with C9orf72 expansions (755 families), 1179 with GRN mutations (483 families, 130 different mutations), and 791 with MAPT mutations (254 families, 67 different mutations). Mean age at symptom onset and at death was 49·5 years (SD 10·0; onset) and 58·5 years (11·3; death) in the MAPT group, 58·2 years (9·8; onset) and 65·3 years (10·9; death) in the C9orf72 group, and 61·3 years (8·8; onset) and 68·8 years (9·7; death) in the GRN group. Mean disease duration was 6·4 years (SD 4·9) in the C9orf72 group, 7·1 years (3·9) in the GRN group, and 9·3 years (6·4) in the MAPT group. Individual age at onset and at death was significantly correlated with both parental age at onset and at death and with mean family age at onset and at death in all three groups, with a stronger correlation observed in the MAPT group (r=0·45 between individual and parental age at onset, r=0·63 between individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·58 between individual and parental age at death, and r=0·69 between individual and mean family age at death) than in either the C9orf72 group (r=0·32 individual and parental age at onset, r=0·36 individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·38 individual and parental age at death, and r=0·40 individual and mean family age at death) or the GRN group (r=0·22 individual and parental age at onset, r=0·18 individual and mean family age at onset, r=0·22 individual and parental age at death, and r=0·32 individual and mean family age at death). Modelling showed that the variability in age at onset and at death in the MAPT group was explained partly by the specific mutation (48%, 95% CI 35-62, for age at onset; 61%, 47-73, for age at death), and even more by family membership (66%, 56-75, for age at onset; 74%, 65-82, for age at death). In the GRN group, only 2% (0-10) of the variability of age at onset and 9% (3-21) of that of age of death was explained by the specific mutation, whereas 14% (9-22) of the variability of age at onset and 20% (12-30) of that of age at death was explained by family membership. In the C9orf72 group, family membership explained 17% (11-26) of the variability of age at onset and 19% (12-29) of that of age at death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation: Our study showed that age at symptom onset and at death of people with genetic frontotemporal dementia is influenced by genetic group and, particularly for MAPT mutations, by the specific mutation carried and by family membership. Although estimation of age at onset will be an important factor in future pre-symptomatic therapeutic trials for all three genetic groups, our study suggests that data from other members of the family will be particularly helpful only for individuals with MAPT mutations. Further work in identifying both genetic and environmental factors that modify phenotype in all groups will be important to improve such estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funding: UK Medical Research Council, National Institute for Health Research, and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Society.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Increased Risk of Melanoma in C9ORF72 Repeat Expansion Carriers - A Case-Control Study</title>
      <link>/website/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) are considered part of the same pathological spectrum. There is an increased risk of ALS in patients who have had melanoma. The risk of FTLD in melanoma (or cancer) patients is unknown. We aimed to study if C9ORF72 expansion is linked to a higher prevalence of melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We selected patients with a diagnosis in the ALS-FTLD spectrum who were tested for pathogenic mutations. Medical history was reviewed, to identify those with pathologically documented melanomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: We included 189 patients. Sixty-two had identified pathogenic mutations (39 C9ORF72). C9ORF72 carriers had a significantly higher risk of melanoma (odds ratio = 24.709; P &amp;lt; 0.007). There was no association with phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: These findings suggest that patients with a history of melanoma may have an increased probability of carrying a C9ORF72 repeat expansion. ALS or FTLD carriers of C9ORF72 should undergo surveillance for skin changes. Muscle Nerve 59:362-365, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: C9ORF72; amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; frontotemporal dementia; melanoma; skin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
