<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Memory | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/tags/memory/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/memory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Memory</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Memory</title>
      <link>/tags/memory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminative Capacity and Construct Validity of the Clock Drawing Test in Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: The aim of this study was to analyze the psychometric and diagnostic properties of the Clock Drawing Test (CDT), scored according to the Babins, Rouleau, and Cahn scoring systems, for Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) screening, and develop corresponding cutoff scores. Additionally, we assessed the construct validity of the CDT through exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis. 
Methods: We developed a cross-sectional study of ambulatory MCI and AD patients, divided in two clinical groups (450 MCI and 250 mild AD patients) and a normal control group (N = 400). All participants were assessed with the CDT, Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) for convergent validity. 
Results: The selected scoring systems presented adequate validity and reliability values. The proposed cutoff scores showed 60 to 65% sensitivity and 58 to 62% specificity to identify MCI patients. The corresponding values for AD were 84 to 90% sensitivity and 76 to 78% specificity. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis revealed that the Babins scoring system had good construct validity and allowed us to propose a three-factor model for this system. 
Conclusions: Our results confirmed the complexity of the CDT and support it as a cognitive screening instrument particularly sensitive to AD. The use of the CDT with MCI patients should be interpreted with more caution due to the lower sensitivity and specificity for milder forms of cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Mild Cognitive Impairment; Neuropsychological tests; cognitive screening; confirmatory factor analysis; exploratory factor analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog) - Normative Data for the Portuguese Population</title>
      <link>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale is a brief battery developed to assess cognitive functioning in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease that encompasses the core characteristics of cognitive decline (e.g. memory, language, praxis, constructive ability and orientation). The early detection, as well as the monitoring of cognitive decline along disease progression, is extremely important in clinical care and interventional research. The main goals of the present study were to analyze the psychometric properties of the Portuguese version of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale, and to establish normative values for the Portuguese population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: The Portuguese version of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was administered to 223 cognitively healthy participants according to a standard assessment protocol consisting of the Mini-Mental State Examination, the Montreal Cognitive Assessment and the Adults and Older Adults Functional Assessment Inventory. Normal performance on the assessment protocol was the inclusion criteria for the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale revealed good psychometric properties when used in the Portuguese population. Age was the main predictor of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total score (R2 = 0.123), whereas the influence of education level was lower (R2 = 0.027). These two variables explained 14.4% of the variance on the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale scores and were used to stratify the normative values for the Portuguese population presented here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: On the total sample, the average total score in the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was 6 points. The normative data were determined according to age and educational level as these were the sociodemographic variables that significantly contributed to the prediction of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total scores, explaining 14.4% of their variance. The normative data are of the utmost importance to ensure proper use of this battery in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer Disease; Cognitive Dysfunction; Neuropsychological Tests; Portugal; Surveys and Questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
