<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>José Beato-Coelho | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/authors/jose-beato-coelho/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/authors/jose-beato-coelho/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>José Beato-Coelho</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>José Beato-Coelho</title>
      <link>/website/authors/jose-beato-coelho/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Headache Intensity Is Associated With Increased White Matter Lesion Burden in CADASIL Patients</title>
      <link>/website/publication/headache-intensity-is-associated-with-increased-white-matter-lesion-burden-in-cadasil-patients/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/headache-intensity-is-associated-with-increased-white-matter-lesion-burden-in-cadasil-patients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract
Objectives: Cerebral autosomal dominant arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy (CADASIL) is the most common hereditary cause of vascular dementia in adults. Migraine is a major symptom of the disease. We aimed to identify clinical and demographical features of the headache associated with increased cerebral lesion burden in a cohort of CADASIL patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Thirty-two patients with CADASIL were enrolled in this cross-sectional study. Demographics data, vascular risk factors and headache characteristics were collected through a structured questionnaire. MRI (3-T) was used to determine white matter hyperintensities burden evaluated by its volume (WMH-V).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Regression analysis showed that age (β = 1.266, 95%CI = [0.805, 1.726], p &amp;lt; 0.001), headache intensity (β = 5.143, 95%CI = [2.362, 7.924], p = 0.001) and female sex (β = 19.727, 95%CI = [8.750, 30.075], p = 0.001) were the main predictors of WMH-V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Age, female sex and headache intensity are associated with increased white matter lesion volume in CADASIL.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single Word Repetition Predicts Long-Term Outcome of Aphasia Caused by an Ischemic Stroke</title>
      <link>/website/publication/single-word-repetition-predicts-long-term-outcome-of-aphasia-caused-by-an-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/single-word-repetition-predicts-long-term-outcome-of-aphasia-caused-by-an-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: Better understanding of clinical predictors of aphasia outcome is of the utmost importance, in patients&amp;rsquo; rehabilitation planning, expectation management, and further physiopathology understanding. We aimed to identify clinical predictors of long-term poststroke aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We conducted a prospective longitudinal observation study of patients with left-Middle Cerebral Artery stroke with aphasia. Patients were evaluated at baseline, day 7 and 6 months with National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) and Aphasia Rapid Test Other demographic variables and vascular risk factors were collected. A linear regression was performed to identify best predictors of aphasia at 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: We included 113 patients with a left hemisphere stroke, with 81 reaching the final evaluation. Aphasia Handicap Score at 6 months was predicted by baseline total NIHSS (β = .077, 95%CI = [.026, .127]. P = .004), infarct volume on CT-scan (β = .009, 95%CI = [.003, .015]. P = .003), single word repetition at baseline (β = .188, 95%CI = [.040, .335]. P = .013), and infection during hospitalization (β = .759, 95%CI = [.263, 1.255]. P = .003).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome in patients with stroke is predicted by a single word repetition task at baseline. Infection during hospitalization has a negative impact on aphasia&amp;rsquo;s outcome at 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/website/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Classical aphasia evaluation scales are too long to use in the context of acute stroke or as a monitoring tool. The Aphasia Rapid Test is a 26-point scale developed as a bedside assessment to rate aphasia severity in acute stroke patients in less than 3 minutes. We aimed to adapt and validate this scale for European Portuguese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: We evaluated 56 acute stroke patients in the first and in the seventh days post-stroke. In the seventh day, patients were evaluated by two independent raters, to evaluate inter-rater agreement. To study concurrent validity, the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was applied to a subset of 20 patients. The predictive ability of the Aphasia Rapid Test was assessed at six months, by the aphasia subscale of the National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Translation to European Portuguese was based in the French and English versions, considering the words&amp;rsquo; utilization frequency. The Chronbach&amp;rsquo;s alpha was 0.796. The concordance coefficient between the two raters was excellent (0.985). Correlation between Aphasia Rapid Test and the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was strong (r = -0.958, p &amp;lt; 0.001). The study through Bland-Altman graphs corroborated the good inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity of the test. The Aphasia Rapid Test score in the first day is an independent predictor of long-term outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: This study provides reliable results for European Portuguese, with adequate internal consistency, inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: The Aphasia Rapid Test is a good tool for the evaluation and monitoring of aphasia in stroke patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
