<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luciano Almendra | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/authors/luciano-almendra/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/luciano-almendra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Luciano Almendra</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Luciano Almendra</title>
      <link>/authors/luciano-almendra/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Increased Risk of Melanoma in C9ORF72 Repeat Expansion Carriers - A Case-Control Study</title>
      <link>/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/increased-risk-of-melanoma-in-c9orf72-repeat-expansion-carriers-a-case-control-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) are considered part of the same pathological spectrum. There is an increased risk of ALS in patients who have had melanoma. The risk of FTLD in melanoma (or cancer) patients is unknown. We aimed to study if C9ORF72 expansion is linked to a higher prevalence of melanoma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We selected patients with a diagnosis in the ALS-FTLD spectrum who were tested for pathogenic mutations. Medical history was reviewed, to identify those with pathologically documented melanomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: We included 189 patients. Sixty-two had identified pathogenic mutations (39 C9ORF72). C9ORF72 carriers had a significantly higher risk of melanoma (odds ratio = 24.709; P &amp;lt; 0.007). There was no association with phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: These findings suggest that patients with a history of melanoma may have an increased probability of carrying a C9ORF72 repeat expansion. ALS or FTLD carriers of C9ORF72 should undergo surveillance for skin changes. Muscle Nerve 59:362-365, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: C9ORF72; amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; frontotemporal dementia; melanoma; skin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tremor Frequency Assessment by iPhone® Applications - Correlation With EMG Analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/tremor-frequency-assessment-by-iphone-applications-correlation-with-emg-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/tremor-frequency-assessment-by-iphone-applications-correlation-with-emg-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tremor frequency analysis is usually performed by EMG studies but accelerometers are progressively being more used. The iPhone® contains an accelerometer and many applications claim to be capable of measuring tremor frequency. We tested three applications in twenty-two patients with a diagnosis of PD, ET and Holmes&amp;rsquo; tremor. EMG needle assessment as well as accelerometry was performed at the same time. There was very strong correlation (Pearson &amp;gt;0.8, p &amp;lt; 0.001) between the three applications, the EMG needle and the accelerometry. Our data suggests the apps LiftPulse®, iSeismometer® and Studymytremor® are a reliable alternative to the EMG for tremor frequency assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: EMG; Tremor; accelerometers; frequency; iPhone; smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
