<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Whipple | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/tags/whipple/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/whipple/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Whipple</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Whipple</title>
      <link>/tags/whipple/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosopagnosia as the Presenting Symptom of Whipple Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/prosopagnosia-as-the-presenting-symptom-of-whipple-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whipple disease is a rare, chronic multisystem infectious disease. The central nervous system (CNS) is secondarily involved in 43% of patients; 5% of patients have isolated or primary CNS involvement. The most frequent CNS symptoms are cognitive changes. Prosopagnosia is an inability to recognize familiar faces, in a person who does not have vision impairments or cognitive alterations. This relatively rare condition is usually related to vascular, traumatic, degenerative, or infectious lesions. We report a 54-year-old woman who presented subacutely with fever, headache, and seizures that led to a diagnosis of infectious meningoencephalitis. She improved temporarily on broad-spectrum antibiotics, but then developed a chronically evolving cognitive impairment with associative prosopagnosia as the major complaint. She had a history of sporadic abdominal pain and mild sacroiliac arthralgia. After a negative duodenal biopsy, we confirmed primary CNS Whipple disease by polymerase chain reaction and brain biopsy. We treated the patient with ceftriaxone for 15 days and then co-trimoxazole for 2 years. At 8-year follow-up, she had no further impairments, but continuing prosopagnosia. To our knowledge, this is the first description of isolated prosopagnosia in a patient with primary CNS Whipple disease. Because CNS Whipple disease can lead to serious, irreversible lesions if not promptly treated, clinicians must suspect the diagnosis, treat with long-term antibiotics, and follow patients carefully to prevent recurrence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
