<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lewy Body Dementia | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/tags/lewy-body-dementia/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/tags/lewy-body-dementia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lewy Body Dementia</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Lewy Body Dementia</title>
      <link>/website/tags/lewy-body-dementia/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validity and Clinical Utility of Different Clock Drawing Test Scoring Systems in Multiple Forms of Dementia</title>
      <link>/website/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clock Drawing Test (CDT) has a known potential for the detection of cognitive impairment in populations with dementia, especially Alzheimer disease (AD). Our aim was to compare the clinical utility of 3 CDT scoring systems (Rouleau, Cahn, and Babins) in several pathologies with cognitive compromise from a tertiary center memory clinic. We selected patients with a clinical diagnosis of mild stage AD, behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia (FTD), vascular dementia (VaD), dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB), and Parkinson disease with dementia (PDD). The results showed significant differences between the several diagnoses with the following pattern of results: AD, DLB &amp;lt; FTD, VaD, PDD. Qualitative analysis of clock drawing errors confirmed the stimulus-bound response as a hallmark of AD, while conceptual deficit was significantly more prevalent in patients with AD and DLB. Our results supported the CDT potential as a cognitive screening measure for mild dementia, particularly sensitive to AD and DLB, especially when we used the Cahn scoring system and its analysis of qualitative errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: cognitive screening; dementia; neuropsychological tests; validation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
