<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diana Duro | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/authors/diana-duro/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/diana-duro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Diana Duro</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar</url>
      <title>Diana Duro</title>
      <link>/authors/diana-duro/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminative Capacity and Construct Validity of the Clock Drawing Test in Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/discriminative-capacity-and-construct-validity-of-the-clock-drawing-test-in-mild-cognitive-impairment-and-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: The aim of this study was to analyze the psychometric and diagnostic properties of the Clock Drawing Test (CDT), scored according to the Babins, Rouleau, and Cahn scoring systems, for Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) screening, and develop corresponding cutoff scores. Additionally, we assessed the construct validity of the CDT through exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis. 
Methods: We developed a cross-sectional study of ambulatory MCI and AD patients, divided in two clinical groups (450 MCI and 250 mild AD patients) and a normal control group (N = 400). All participants were assessed with the CDT, Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) for convergent validity. 
Results: The selected scoring systems presented adequate validity and reliability values. The proposed cutoff scores showed 60 to 65% sensitivity and 58 to 62% specificity to identify MCI patients. The corresponding values for AD were 84 to 90% sensitivity and 76 to 78% specificity. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis revealed that the Babins scoring system had good construct validity and allowed us to propose a three-factor model for this system. 
Conclusions: Our results confirmed the complexity of the CDT and support it as a cognitive screening instrument particularly sensitive to AD. The use of the CDT with MCI patients should be interpreted with more caution due to the lower sensitivity and specificity for milder forms of cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer’s disease; Mild Cognitive Impairment; Neuropsychological tests; cognitive screening; confirmatory factor analysis; exploratory factor analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validity and Clinical Utility of Different Clock Drawing Test Scoring Systems in Multiple Forms of Dementia</title>
      <link>/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/validity-and-clinical-utility-of-different-clock-drawing-test-scoring-systems-in-multiple-forms-of-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clock Drawing Test (CDT) has a known potential for the detection of cognitive impairment in populations with dementia, especially Alzheimer disease (AD). Our aim was to compare the clinical utility of 3 CDT scoring systems (Rouleau, Cahn, and Babins) in several pathologies with cognitive compromise from a tertiary center memory clinic. We selected patients with a clinical diagnosis of mild stage AD, behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia (FTD), vascular dementia (VaD), dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB), and Parkinson disease with dementia (PDD). The results showed significant differences between the several diagnoses with the following pattern of results: AD, DLB &amp;lt; FTD, VaD, PDD. Qualitative analysis of clock drawing errors confirmed the stimulus-bound response as a hallmark of AD, while conceptual deficit was significantly more prevalent in patients with AD and DLB. Our results supported the CDT potential as a cognitive screening measure for mild dementia, particularly sensitive to AD and DLB, especially when we used the Cahn scoring system and its analysis of qualitative errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: cognitive screening; dementia; neuropsychological tests; validation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog) - Normative Data for the Portuguese Population</title>
      <link>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/alzheimers-disease-assessment-scale-cognitive-subscale-adas-cog-normative-data-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale is a brief battery developed to assess cognitive functioning in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease that encompasses the core characteristics of cognitive decline (e.g. memory, language, praxis, constructive ability and orientation). The early detection, as well as the monitoring of cognitive decline along disease progression, is extremely important in clinical care and interventional research. The main goals of the present study were to analyze the psychometric properties of the Portuguese version of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale, and to establish normative values for the Portuguese population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: The Portuguese version of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was administered to 223 cognitively healthy participants according to a standard assessment protocol consisting of the Mini-Mental State Examination, the Montreal Cognitive Assessment and the Adults and Older Adults Functional Assessment Inventory. Normal performance on the assessment protocol was the inclusion criteria for the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale revealed good psychometric properties when used in the Portuguese population. Age was the main predictor of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total score (R2 = 0.123), whereas the influence of education level was lower (R2 = 0.027). These two variables explained 14.4% of the variance on the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale scores and were used to stratify the normative values for the Portuguese population presented here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: On the total sample, the average total score in the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale was 6 points. The normative data were determined according to age and educational level as these were the sociodemographic variables that significantly contributed to the prediction of the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale total scores, explaining 14.4% of their variance. The normative data are of the utmost importance to ensure proper use of this battery in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer Disease; Cognitive Dysfunction; Neuropsychological Tests; Portugal; Surveys and Questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prognosis of Early-Onset vs. Late-Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment -  Comparison of Conversion Rates and Its Predictors</title>
      <link>/publication/prognosis-of-early-onset-vs.-late-onset-mild-cognitive-impairment-comparison-of-conversion-rates-and-its-predictors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/prognosis-of-early-onset-vs.-late-onset-mild-cognitive-impairment-comparison-of-conversion-rates-and-its-predictors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Despite having the same histopathological characteristics, early-onset and late-onset Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) patients show some distinct clinical and neuropsychological profiles. Early Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment (EOMCI) is a less characterized group. The aim of this study is to characterize MCI probably due to AD in terms of the clinical, genetic, Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers profile and conversion rate of EOMCI, compared to the late-onset form (LOMCI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: 159 MCI patients were divided in two groups: 52 EOMCI (onset &amp;lt; 65 years) and 107 LOMCI (onset ≥ 65 years). We investigated differences in neuropsychological scores, clinical variables, ApoE genotype, CSF biomarkers (Aβ42, t-Tau and p-Tau) in both groups. Conversion was ascertained during follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: EOMCI showed a longer duration of symptoms prior to the first evaluation (EOMCI = 4.57 vs. LOMCI = 3.31, p = 0.008) and scored higher on the subjective memory complaints scale (9.91 vs. 7.85, p = 0.008), but performed better in brief cognitive tests (27.81 vs. 26.51, p &amp;lt; 0.001 in Mini-Mental State Examination; 19.84 vs. 18.67, p = 0.005 in Montreal Cognitive Assessment) than LOMCI. ApoE genotype distribution and CSF biomarker profile were similar in both groups, as was the conversion risk. Lower Aβ42 (Hazard ratio (HR): 0.998, 95% Confidence Interval (CI) = [0.996⁻1.000], p = 0.042), higher t-Tau levels (HR: 1.003, 95%CI = [1.000⁻1.005], p = 0.039) and higher scores in the Alzheimer Disease Assessment Scale-Cognitive (HR: 1.186, 95%CI = [1.083⁻1.299], p = 0.002) increased the risk of conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: Despite differences in memory performance and memory complaints, EOMCI and LOMCI seem to represent indistinct biological groups that do not have a higher risk of conversion to AD or differ in risk factors for conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Alzheimer; MCI; biomarkers; conversion; dementia; early-onset; late-onset; mild cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
