<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>scale | Miguel Tábuas Pereira</title>
    <link>/website/tags/scale/</link>
      <atom:link href="/website/tags/scale/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>scale</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/website/img/avatar</url>
      <title>scale</title>
      <link>/website/tags/scale/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/website/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/website/publication/aphasia-rapid-test-translation-adaptation-and-validation-studies-for-the-portuguese-population/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Classical aphasia evaluation scales are too long to use in the context of acute stroke or as a monitoring tool. The Aphasia Rapid Test is a 26-point scale developed as a bedside assessment to rate aphasia severity in acute stroke patients in less than 3 minutes. We aimed to adapt and validate this scale for European Portuguese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material and methods: We evaluated 56 acute stroke patients in the first and in the seventh days post-stroke. In the seventh day, patients were evaluated by two independent raters, to evaluate inter-rater agreement. To study concurrent validity, the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was applied to a subset of 20 patients. The predictive ability of the Aphasia Rapid Test was assessed at six months, by the aphasia subscale of the National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Translation to European Portuguese was based in the French and English versions, considering the words&amp;rsquo; utilization frequency. The Chronbach&amp;rsquo;s alpha was 0.796. The concordance coefficient between the two raters was excellent (0.985). Correlation between Aphasia Rapid Test and the Lisbon Aphasia Examination Battery was strong (r = -0.958, p &amp;lt; 0.001). The study through Bland-Altman graphs corroborated the good inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity of the test. The Aphasia Rapid Test score in the first day is an independent predictor of long-term outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion: This study provides reliable results for European Portuguese, with adequate internal consistency, inter-rater agreement and concurrent validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: The Aphasia Rapid Test is a good tool for the evaluation and monitoring of aphasia in stroke patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
